right now crews are working to restore
power to thousands of people after a
tornado moved through Central Texas last
night from the ground up repairs were
being made and branches and debris were
being cleared everywhere I look around
me there's destruction it felt like
eternity and it was over we could hear
it and like feel it in the building we
are out here in West Temple where there
is so much destruction the city of
Temple was the area hardest
it so you want to know more about the
tornado that hit Temple Texas in May of
this year stay tuned to find out more hi
and welcome to my channel I'm Andrea
dudic associate broker and realtor with
Vista Real Estate here in Central Texas
if this is your first time to my Channel
Please Subscribe below and click the
Bell icon so that you can be the first
to know about the latest market trends
and happenings in the area so May 22nd
in Temple started off just like any
other Texas day the weather here can be
very finicky it can start off beautiful
and sunny in the morning and then by the
end of the day you've got yourself a
storm it's just expected and everyone
knows that's what happens here that day
we were under I believe an all day
tornado watch uh which is very common I
am not originally from the area so that
was something very new to me when I came
here 8 years ago from Las Vegas Texans
are very comfortable and familiar with
the idea of tornadoes I can actually
recall one time hearing a tornado watch
and I was in the bathroom um with the
door closed and my husband was sitting
outside with a cocktail looking at the
weather and I said what are you doing
and he said well we're in Texas this is
just a tornado watch we just hang out
and watch like we'll get plenty of
notice before it comes but that is very
much how things operate here in my
experience so that day I was at work in
this used to be office or building I
have two toddlers they go to daycare
across the street went and picked them
up around 5:00 my husband and I went to
Walmart across the street from there
went grocery shopping everyone else is
doing their grocery shopping tornado
watch is still a thing we drove home and
as we pull into the driveway we get a
tornado warning and as this is happening
you're getting updates we are on a
particular Channel That's updating us
where the storm is hitting where's the
tornado most likely to hit so we're
watching this and the tornado did hit
and um when we came out of our storm
shelter a bunch of trees had been
knocked down but there was really not a
ton of damage to our house I think we
had a bathroom window that was blown out
we did have a lot of oak trees that had
been knocked over but overall it was
okay well throughout Temple um there was
really one main strip which this office
was on that strip that was hit pretty
heavily by the tornado and it has been 4
months since the tornado the community
has completely rebuilt itself so that's
been really cool to see we had a lot of
roof repairs every deal that I had under
contract roofers had to come out do roof
repairs we had to negotiate roof
Replacements get insurance involved a
lot of fences had to be repaired but we
just handled it I wouldn't say business
is usual but really everything is
figureoutable is a term that I like we
can figure out everything and so we did
and so did the community in the end the
tornado that hit Temple was relatively
mild compared to other tornadoes that
have occurred here in Texas since 1950
over 9,800 tornadoes have been reported
across Texas according to the National
Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration
tornadoes have touched down in every one
of Texas's 254 counties Harris County
Home to Houston has recorded the highest
number with 250 tornadoes this is
significantly more than hail County
north of LEC which has seen 133
tornadoes in the same period it's
important to note that over 75% of
tornadoes are classified as weak either
rated F0 ef0 or F1 ef1 and since 1950
only six tornadoes in Texas have been
rated F5 with the strongest tornado in
Bell County which is where I'm currently
based being rated F3 the tornado that
occurred here in May was an ef2 tornado
so relatively mild I think the biggest
takeaways from this video are one
tornadoes do happen but they're relative
relatively mild and weak two we have
precautions in place to keep everyone
safe and notify you when tornadoes are
happening and then number three is that
nature is nature and every area is going
to come with its risks associated with
living there it's going to be up to you
to determine whether those um benefits
outweigh the risks that Nature's going
to bring if you're looking to move to or
away from the area I'd love to speak
with you I'm Andrea dudic realtor and
assistant broker with fist real estate
guiding your next move with Insight care
and clear communication don't forget to
subscribe hit the bell and find my
contact information down below